Good afternoon. Today's דף *daf* is קלח *Kuf Lamed Chet* 138. We
pick up at the very bottom of קלז עמוד ב *Kuf Lamed
Zayin Amud Bet*, two lines from the bottom. So we had started
a totally new topic after we've dealt with ברית מילה *Brit Milah*
extensively and the topic was about putting a sieve on the top
of some type of a jar or some type of a vessel,
and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* says you can put it
up on יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov* and the חכמים chachamim
*Chachamim* said you can't. The גמרא gemara *Gemara* framed that as a
type of an אהל עראי ohel arai. *Ohel Aray*, which is pretty
funny, you know, it would have never occurred to us that stretching
something like, you know, on top of a jar is an אהל
ohel, *Ohel*, but that's how the גמרא gemara *Gemara* considered it and
said that the reason רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* allowed it
was because he would allow you to do even מכשירי אוכל נפש
*Machshirei Ochel Nefesh*, even preparatory things for food on יום טוב Yom
Tov. *Yom Tov*, even things that could have been done ערב יום
טוב *Erev Yom Tov*. So that way of framing it certainly makes
it sound like it could even be a biblical problem of אהל
ohel. *Ohel* that you have to make recourse to this principle of
מכשירי אוכל נפש *Machshirei Ochel Nefesh*. But we will see where the
גמרא gemara *Gemara* goes with it because the חכמים chachamim *Chachamim* say
you cannot do it on יום טוב *Yom Tov*. So now the
גמרא gemara *Gemara* says וחכמים אומרים *V’Chachamim Omrim*, two lines from the
bottom, איבעיא להו Iba'ya l'hu, *Ibayah Lehu*, so they asked the question:
תלא מאי *Tala Mai*? What happens if you actually did put this
sieve, you know, stretched this piece of cloth on top of this
jar on יום טוב *Yom Tov*? What would be the הלכה halakhic
*halacha*, is it a real דאורייתא d'oraisa? *De’oraita*, what's the story? So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אמר רב יוסף Amar Rav Yosef *Amar
Rav Yosef*, תלא חייב חטאת chayav chatas. *Tala Chayav Chatat*. Yeah, you're
חייב chayav *chayav* a sin offering. We'll see something very similar in
a minute coming up as well,
that if you do it you're חייב chayav *chayav* a sin offering
even though, again, now this is an interesting part about these last
פרקים *perakim* in שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* where it says don't do this,
don't do this, don't do that, it doesn't tell you is it
דאורייתא d'oraisa *De’oraita* or דרבנן d'rabbanan, *Derabbanan* and it's left for the
אמוראים *Amoraim* and for the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* to speculate whether it's
a דאורייתא *De’oraita* or דרבנן derabbanan *Derabbanan*. So he says this is
a real דאורייתא *De’oraita*. אמר ליה אביי Amar leh Abaye, *Amar Lei
Abaye*, what, of אהל ohel *Ohel*? Which is pretty extreme, right, because
an אהל ohel. *Ohel* you would think, I mean, it's something that's
more of a structure than a vessel. This is a vessel even
if, you know, technically speaking, it's got some type of a roof
and it's got whatever the parameters are, fundamentally it's a vessel, it's
not a structure.
So he says it's not the actual lid of the jar, right?
Right, it's not, correct, it's not like screwing the lid of a
jar on. It's a basically, you know, you have something that's just
a pitcher and you're taking something that's not part of its normal
cover and you're stretching it over it tightly, you know, but still
it's still more in the vessel.
Saran wrap would be a good example, yeah, Saran wrap would be
a good example, you take something, you tightly put it on top
of an opening and it's now, I mean, it's not even there
to serve as an אהל ohel *Ohel*. An אהל ohel *Ohel* is
there to serve to protect the things underneath it. I mean, I
guess you could say Saran wrap does, but that's more by keeping
out the air than by providing like a protection, well, a little
bit Saran wrap maybe, but it's certainly not the point of a
sieve. But right, you know, I think if you physically think what
it is, that's a good parallel. So it's a little wild. So
אמר ליה Amar lei: אביי Abaye *Amar Lei Abaye* back to רב
Rav. יוסף *Rav Yosef*, אלא מעתה ela me'ata תלא כוזא בסיכתא הכי
נמי דמיחייב *Ela Meata Tala Kuza Besikta Hachi Nami DeMechayav*?
So what, like you mean if you hang a jar
from a nail, would you be חייב chayav *chayav*? What, just because
you suspend something? Now obviously there's a difference, hanging a jar from
a nail, you're not making a roof over something, but nevertheless, his
point is essentially this: come on, this is trivial, you can't call
this a מלאכה melachah. *melacha*, you know, you're just putting something on
top of a vessel. אלא ela אמר אביי Amar Abaye, מדרבנן mi'derabbanan,
היא *Ela Amar Abaye Midrabbanan Hi*, it's Rabbinic. עין שלא יעשה כדרך
שהוא עושה בחול *Ein Shelo Yaaseh Kederech Sheoseh Bechol*. Now even when
he says it's Rabbinic, you notice he didn't say it's like a
Rabbinic אהל ohel. *Ohel*. He even made it like even more of
a secondary concern, that it's just it's similar to weekday types of
activities. Now exactly what constitutes עובדא דחול uvda d'chol *Uvda Dechol*, doing
things as if you're doing it in the weekday is a big
question because it sort of, you know, begs the question, what's considered
weekday activities that's not associated to a מלאכה *melacha*? So it could
be it is associated to a מלאכה *melacha*, the מלאכה *melacha* of,
you know, sifting wine, right, because that is, could be a type
of a בורר borer *borer* and so on. So
this is associated with that type of an activity,
but it's not exactly always clear what falls into this category of
עובדא דחול uvda d'chol. *Uvda Dechol*. But that's what אביי Abaye *Abaye*
said, he doesn't even call it a Rabbinic אהל ohel. *Ohel*.
So they're both debating here in our משנה mishna *Mishnah* עובדא דחול
uvda d'chol.
*Uvda Dechol*. Right. And then when רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*
says you're allowed to do it on יום טוב *Yom Tov*, it's
not a בי די חדוש *bi de chiddush* because basically it's עובדא
דחול *Uvda Dechol* and anyway it's עובדא דחול *Uvda Dechol* relating to
food and you're allowed to do food stuff on יום טוב *Yom
Tov*. So right, I mean, I'll give you an interesting debate actually
about עובדא דחול *Uvda Dechol* on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*, which is that
the שלחן ערוך פוסק'נס *Shulchan Aruch paskens* based on, I think it's
a תרומת הדשן *Terumat HaDeshen*, that you can't cut cheese with a
certain type of a knife or saw on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbat* because
of עובדא דחול *Uvda Dechol*. Like a cheese, well, it's not exactly
clear, I think I'm not remembering the exact specifics. Anyway, based on
that, a number of אחרונים *Acharonim* say, I believe the שמירת שבת
Shabbos, *Shemirat Shabbat* pretty consistently says, that you can't use any kitchen,
any like labor-saving kitchen devices on שבת Shabbat. *Shabbat* because it's עובדא
דחול *Uvda Dechol*. So now why would a labor-saving device define something
as עובדא דחול *Uvda Dechol* unless you feel like שבת Shabbat. *Shabbat*
would be having being very like... primitive and using any type of
a gadget is עובדא דחול. Anyway רב משה Rav Moshe disagrees. He
says that's only עובדא דחול in that one case because it would
be the type the type of thing that would use like in
large-scale production. But things that I use just in the kitchen sort
of like you know on small scale just because you have a
use a kitchen-saving gadget does not make it עובדא דחול. But it's
a real question how to define what the parameters of there is.
But that's where אביי Abaye is moving with this thing. Moving it
seeming to be out of אהל, ohel. but now we're going to
go back and sort of reintroduce אהל. ohel So let's take a
look. מאן כי אביי חומרי מתניתא ותניס. man ki Abaye chumrei masnisa
usnis.
אביי sort of gathered the... now חומרי chumrei here does not mean
חומרות. chumros. חומרי chumrei means like the bundles. Bundles of ברייתות braisos
or משניות mishnayos and he taught, meaning he gathered together different teachings
and he organized them into different groupings and he taught them. And
here's was a couple that he gathered together. הגוד והמשמרת כילה וכסא
גלן לא יעשה. hagod vehameshmeret kila vechisei galen lo yaaseh.
The following things are taught in various ברייתות braisos that you can't
do on שבת Shabbos or יום טוב. גוד god which is a
type of a... of like a canteen like a flask that they
would do they would store wine in it but apparently what they
would do is they would stretch it out on like poles like
they would do for like big you know big caravans you know
big groups and they would have base so it'd be a leather
type of a pouch and they but they would ex- put it
stretch it out over poles so apparently the wind would blow and
keep it cool and so on. So you're suspending this big leather
thing you know and apparently that's could be like an אהל ohel
I mean if it weren't that the reason you were doing it
was just to keep this leather pouch cool. So that's the גוד.
god. משמרת mishmeret is our משנה about the sieve on top of
the vessel. כילה kila is a is a what do you call
it is like a canopy over bed and וכסא גלן vechisei galen
is also some type of a chair that you would essentially you
know erect and put like a put the seat on. So imagine
you would like like you have let's say a folding chair you
would open up the legs like a director's chair. Okay you'd open
up the legs and then you'd stretch over the leather on top
of it. So the leather also is a type of a roof
but it's done to make a chair. Okay so those types of
things you should not do.
But normally say a folding chair?
Well we're about to get to that so hold on. Okay. So
לא יעשה lo yaaseh you should not do them on שבת Shabbos,
or יום טוב. ואם עשה פטור אבל אסור. veim asah patur aval
assur. Thank you so much. And if you so called out there
and if you did it you're exempt but it's but it's forbidden
but you're exempt it's not biblical any of those it's not a
real biblical אהל. ohel, So notice here by the way though גוד
god it doesn't seem like we're just in generic עובדא
דחול. These are types of things that are rabbinic אהל ohel because
but again it's not a biblical אהל ohel. because it's not permanent
you're not making it to serve as an אהל. ohel. So those
types of things are rabbinic. אבל aval
פטור אבל אסור. patur aval assur. אהל
קבע לא יעשה ואם עשה חייב חטאת. ohel keva lo yaaseh veim
asah chayav chatas. Now permanent אהלים ohels these are all temporary because
you you know you spread it and you undo it. Something that's
permanent you should not do and if you do you're חייב חטאת.
chayav chatas, Now part again there are two things that make the
first case better. One is that it's temporary and the other is
that it's not even really made for the function of an אהל.
ohel. Okay so it's not exactly clear if in order to be
חייב chayav. if you need it not only to be permanent but
also to function as an אהל. ohel, But anyway in the first
cases it's only rabbinic. אבל aval and here's what's even permissible
מיטה וכסא וטרסקאל mita vechisei vetraskal a bed. Now רש"י Rashi says
the bed case is just that you have this a bed that's
vertical you know you sort of put it up on you know
they used to have those fold beds that fold into a closet
or whatever and then you lower it down. A Murphy's bed. And
then you lower it down. So when you lower it down it's
think it's like a table that was leaning against the wall and
you lowered it down. So you have an אהל ohel, underneath the
table. Okay but you didn't even erect it you just sort of
set it upright. Okay you didn't even like make something. Okay that's
the bed. וכסא טרסקאל. vechisei traskal. כסא טרסקאל chisei traskal is essentially
a type of a folding chair. Okay so that's like a folder
that's like a director's chair where actually it's all attached and you
just open it up it's all on hinges. So something where you're
not making something new it's all already hinges and you're just opening
it up. You could also say a folding table would be part
of this. דאסלא. da'asla. אסלא asla is a is basically a chair
used for toilet. It's like the folding chair but it has a
hole in the middle. Okay so all these types of things מותרין
לתתם לכתחילה mutarin letasam lechatchila you can do it לכתחילה. lechatchila. And
this becomes very important principles about making an אהל ohel which is
something that's already essentially made and on hinges and structure and you're
just opening up. Well okay umbrella's a very good question. There's a
whole history to umbrella and many פוסקים poskim say that if we
were dealing with umbrella you know you know afresh nowadays we would
have said it's מותר mutar but it has a whole history of
being treated as אסור. assur. But something like a folding table or
like a canopy over a baby carriage. Okay all these types of
things that are essentially on hinges. Now again Part of what makes
all these cases better in addition to the fact that they're all
already, you know, sort of already made and just have to be
opened, is also that they're not even being made for the purpose
of an אהל, ohel. right? All these things like a chair, whatever,
an אהל ohel is that the top serves the stuff underneath.
But no, if you do it over a baby, it serves...
I understand, so I'm saying to apply it to a baby, an
awning of a baby carriage is a little bit of a jump
because there it's doing to serve as an אהל. ohel? Okay, but
nevertheless, you know, without giving direct פסק, psak, but basically things on
hinges and that are already made and just requires opening them up
are really, are really okay.
What about a hat with a big brim for the purpose of
making shade?
We are going to talk about that when we turn the page,
so hold off on that. Okay, today is a lot about אהל.
ohel. Okay, so ואין נותנין תליה בשבת, v'ein nosnim t'liya b'Shabbos,
but first we have to deal with going back to a בורר
borer type of a case. Okay, so don't worry though, we're getting
back to אהל. ohel, You can't put wine in a sieve on
שבת. Shabbat. איבעיא להו, they asked the question: שימר מאי? shimmer mai?
What happens if you actually do sieve the wine, is that the
way you say sieved, sift the wine? Anyway, so אמר רב כהנא
השימר חייב חטאת. Amar Rav Kahana: Ashimmer chayav chatas.
Like before we said if you do this, what? חייב חטאת, chayav
chatas, sin offering, it's a biblical violation. Of what? No, no, no,
of בורר borer, or something like בורר, borer, we'll see in a
minute. Okay, מתקיף לה רב ששת Maskif lah Rav Sheshes or ששת
Sheshes asked, מי איכא מידי דרבנן מחייבי חטאת ורבי אליעזר שרי לכתחילה?
mi ika midi d'rabbanan michayeiv chatas Rabbi Eliezer shari l'chatchila?
How could this be? רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says if it's already
set up you can do it לכתחילה l'chatchila on שבת, Shabbat. and
the חכמים chachamim say don't do it. So don't do it, I'd
be prepared to say don't do it means דרבנן, but to say
they argue to opposite extremes, don't do it דאורייתא? So is that
really possible? מתקיף לה רב יוסף אלמה לא? Maskif lah Rav Yosef:
Alama lo?
Why not? הרי עיר של זהב. Harei ir shel zahav. Remember that?
The golden city, the tiara, the golden tiara. רבי מאיר מחייב חטאת,
Rabbi Meir michayeiv chatas, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you're חייב chayav,
a sin offering, ורבי אליעזר שרי לכתחילה, v'Rabbi Eliezer shari l'chatchila, and
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer allowed it even לכתחילה. l'chatchila.
מאי היא? Mai hi? What is that? דתניא D'tanya because we taught
in a
ברייתא, baraisa, לא תצא אשה בעיר של זהב, lo tetzei isha b'ir
shel zahav, a woman should not go out with this golden tiara,
ואם יצאה חייבת חטאת דברי רבי מאיר, v'im yatzsa chayava chatas divrei
Rabbi Meir, and if she goes out she's חייבת חטאת chayava chatas
which is רבי מאיר's's Rabbi Meir words. Because רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says it's not normal, you know, normal women don't wear it. So
therefore, even if you're wearing it for the purpose of ornamentation, it's
considered to be not a recognized objective type of clothery clothing or
ornament, and therefore you're חייב chayav חטאת, which is hard to understand,
but anyway, that's not our פרק, perek, we dealt with that a
long time ago. וחכמים אומרים לא תצא, V'chachamim omrim: Lo tetzei, she
shouldn't go out because she might take it off to show her
friends, ואם יצאה פטורה v'im yatza petura and if she goes out
she's exempt. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, now רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says: יצאה אשה בעיר של זהב לכתחילה, yatza isha b'ir shel
zahav l'chatchila, she can go out from the outset because a) it's
jewelry and b) we're not afraid she'll take it off. So you
see that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it's מותר mutar and the
חכמים chachamim say it's חייב chayav actually, it happens to be the
exact same מן דאמרי, man d'amarim, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer saying מותר
mutar and the חכמים saying חייב. chayav So the גמרא Gemara says
אמר
ליה Amar lei: אביי, אביי said back, מי סברת רבי אליעזר אדרבי
מאיר קאי? Mi savrat Rabbi Eliezer ad Rabbi Meir kai? How do
you know רבי Rebbi אליעזר is directly responding to רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir who says חייב, chayav. דאמר חייבת חטאת? d'amar chayavas chatas? אדרבנן
קאי, Ad rabbanan kai, maybe he's responding to the Rabbis, דאמרי פטור
אבל אסור, d'amri patur aval assur, the Rabbis say it's exempt but
don't do it מדרבנן, ואמר להו איהו מותר לכתחילה v'amar lehu ihu
mutar l'chatchila and he says to them it's מותר לכתחילה. mutar l'chatchila.
Now, what type of an answer is that? Fine, meaning like literally
he's not, you're not juxtaposing חייב chayav with מותר. mutar. Right? Literally
you're juxtaposing חייב chayav. with אסור, assur, or then with רבי אליעזר
you're juxtaposing אסור assur with מותר. mutar. So you're not literally juxtaposing
the extremes. But nevertheless, their actual הלכה halacha positions are still exact
opposite extremes. So you look at this little תוספות, Tosafos, right, מי
סברת רבי אליעזר קאי אדרבי מאיר, mi savrat Rabbi Eliezer kai ad
Rabbi Meir, לא ידע רבי מאי קמשני, lo yada רבי Rebbi mai
kamashani, says רבי who's likely referring to the author of the תוספות,
Tosafos, whatever. He says he doesn't understand what type of an answer
this is. Big deal. So the footnote basically says, if you look
at like the bottom, it actually says in the brackets here: נראה
לפירושא דאף על גב דלא קאי ארבי מאיר מכל מקום הדבר תמוה
איך יחלוק בסוף ובקצה כל כך, nireh l'perusha d'af al gav d'lo
kai a'Rabbi Meir, mikol makom hadavar tamuah, eich yachlok b'sof u'vekatzeh kol
kach, right? So it's very strange, תוספות Tosafos doesn't know what the
גמרא Gemara is saying. Wonderful. So literally they're not juxtaposing the extreme
positions, but still you have one position says חייב chayav. and one
position says מותר. mutar. That's a pretty big extreme. Anyway the גמרא
Gemara doesn't go back to that. Then the גמרא Gemara seems to
be happy with the possibility that רבי אליעזר could say it's מותר
mutar and the חכמים could say it's חייב. chayav? So now that
it's חייב chayav. it wants to know why you're חייב. chayav, משום
מאי מתרינן ביה? Mishum mai matrin bei? What type of התראה hasra'ah
do you give the person? Which is a question about like what
category of אב מלאכה av melacha does it fall into. So finally
we're getting back to the categories of אב מלאכה, av melacha, but
we sort of have, you know, haven't been talking about that for
a while. So רבה אמר משום בורר. Raba amar mishum borer. רבה
Raba says בורר, borer? which stands to reason, right? Why shouldn't it
be בורר? borer רבי
זירא אמר משום מרקד. Rabbi Zeira amar mishum meraked. מרקד meraked is
sifting. Now בורר borer and sifting are pretty similar, right? בורר Boreir.
is you would do is you would take out, like sift out
by hand usually the pebbles or whatever from the grain, and then
the sifting would be after you would crush the grain, you would
sift it to separate the wheat from the chaff. Right? I mean
actually the earlier stage... as well. So the גמרא Gemara even says
that there are three מלאכות Melachot that are all pretty much at
various types of a בורר. Boreir, There's בורר, Boreir. זורה, Zoreh, and
מרקד. Meraqeid. זורה Zoreh is when you throw it up and the
wind blows away the chaff and so on, and then when you
crush it and then you do a sifting. So anyway, so the
גמרא Gemara basically says even though they are pretty similar, we have
it because we got to get to thirty-nine. So here they're debating
which one it falls under. Now certainly it seems it falls much
more under מרקד, Meraqeid, right? Because מרקד Meraqeid is number one, what
you do by מרקד Meraqeid when you're sifting is you're sifting stuff
that was a natural part of the food and you're using a
sieve. And here with the wine presumably,
although maybe there's impurities, maybe you're trying to sift out little thing
dirt that fell into it, but presumably you're sifting out the lees,
the little pieces of grapes, which is a natural part of the
food and you're using a sieve. So certainly it would seem that
it's much more like מרקד Meraqeid than it is like בורר. Boreir.
Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says about what the reason for
this debate is.
אמר רבא Amar Rava said רבא, Rava, כוותי דידי מסתברא, Kevati didi
mistabra, it makes sense like me that it's בורר. Boreir? מה דרכו
של בורר? Ma darko shel Boreir? What's the normal way of בורר?
Boreir. נוטל אוכל ומניח פסולת. Notel ochel u'maniach pesolet. You take the
food and you leave the פסולת pesolet behind. אף הכא נמי נוטל
את האוכל ומניח את הפסולת. Af hacha nami notel et ha'ochel u'maniach
et hapesolet. Here too, you take the food in the sense that
the wine is what is coming out and you leave the פסולת
pesolet behind because that gets stuck at the top of the sieve.
So you're extracting the wine from the mixture. אמר רב זירא Amar
Rav Zeira so said רב זירא, Rav Zeira, כוותי דידי מסתברא, Kevati
didi mistabra, no like me it makes more sense. מה דרכו של
מרקד? Ma darko shel Meraqeid? What's the way of sifting? פסולת מלמעלה
ואוכל מלמטה. Pesolet mil'ma'ala v'ochel mil'mata. The פסולת pesolet is above and
the food is below.
אף הכא נמי פסולת מלמעלה ואוכל מלמטה. Af hacha nami pesolet mil'ma'ala
v'ochel mil'mata. The פסולת pesolet is above and the food is below.
It's pretty, pretty funny because it's totally like מרקד. Meraqeid. It also
seems to me that מרקד Meraqeid also you're removing the food, you're
sifting out, you're getting the food to fall through the holes, so
you're also sifting out the food, you're taking out the food from
the פסולת. pesolet. So רש״י Rashi says, if you look at רש״י,
Rashi, I really don't understand this. רש״י Rashi says where
is רש״י? Rashi?
דנוטל אוכל ומניח פסולת, Denotel ochel u'maniach pesolet, רש״י Rashi about, I
don't know, ten lines before it gets wide, ולרבא הוא הדין נמי
דאיתרו ביה משום מרקד הויא התראה. U'leRava hu hadin nami d'aitru bei
mishum Meraqeid havai hatra'ah. It would also be מרקד. Meraqeid. רבא Rava
isn't denying that it's מרקד, Meraqeid, of course it would be מרקד,
Meraqeid, but he says it's also בורר. Boreir. אבל לרבי זירא יתרו
ביה משום בורר לא הויא התראה, Aval leRabbi Zeira yitru bei mishum
Boreir lo havai hatra'ah, but רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira denies that it's
בורר. Boreir? Why would he deny it's בורר? Boreir? דלא דמי לבורר
שאוכל למטה פסולת למעלה, Delo dami leBoreir she'ochel lemata pesolet lema'ala, מה
שאין כן בבורר, Ma she'ein ken beBoreir, how about בורר? Boreir, כקטנית
שפסולת למטה. K'kitnit she'pesolet lemata. Apparently some types of בורר, Boreir? what
you're doing is you have a mix and you take out, you
got your pile in front of you and you remove the food,
you're not using a sieve. So therefore he's saying, so רש״י Rashi
is saying, look, everybody's got to admit this is a type of
מרקד, Meraqeid, sifting. It's exactly what you do. You put stuff in
a sieve, the good stuff comes out, the bad stuff remains. The
question is can you also call it a בורר? Boreir And he
is saying that according to the second opinion you cannot because a
בורר Boreir. you do more with your hands and you more take
the food and leave the פסולת pesolet behind. So anyway, it's not
exactly similar to בורר. Boreir. It certainly makes sense why it's a
type of מרקד. Meraqeid. It is interesting, I should say, that the
גמרא Gemara considers the possibility that you'd not have been חייב. Why
wouldn't you be חייב? It looks like it's a classic בורר. Boreir.
And I'll also tell you another very interesting הלכה halacha which we
פוסקין paskin by liquids which we basically don't by solids, which is
by liquids we say if the thing was drinkable before using a
sieve, you're allowed to, you're allowed to put it through a sieve
on שבת. Which we would never say by בורר. Boreir Like by
בורר Boreir. we'd say, if you could eat this food without taking
out the little things you don't like, it's okay? No, we say
as long as you're removing פסולת, pesolet, it's a problem of בורר.
Boreir What, right exactly, right? So we don't sort of, now there
are ways in which we say you can eat watermelons or those
types of things, but we by food we never say oh well
since you could have eaten it without it, it's okay. But by
liquids we actually say it, which is why we allow, which is
why we allow, it has to be both you and in general,
okay?
Like let's say orange juice with pulp. Like I don't like the
pulp but some other
people—right, so for you it would be a problem. Okay, yeah, but
רב משה Rav Moshe says for other people who don't, who would
be prepared to drink it with the pulp, then you can use,
then you can sift out the pulp. Okay, and you can use
water filters. So it is very interesting that with liquids there's somewhat
looser parameters than with solids. So the fact that the גמרא Gemara,
here considers, now partly the reason might be because it's happening a
little bit more passively. It's a slightly different thing. It's not בורר
Boreir, you're actively removing or even if you're sifting, you're like vigorously
sifting, whereas here you like pour it through and it just somehow
does it somewhat by itself. But nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara does decide
that it's חייב. It certainly is most similar to sifting, might also
be similar to בורר, and it is interesting to note, which we're
not saying now but we'll see later, that there actually is a
significant area of קולא kula by this, which is that if you
can drink it, if it was drinkable without it, you're allowed to
even do it on שבת.
Like taking טשולנט cholent with a
slotted—right,
so that's a problem, we only say this like— by pure liquids
we don't say this by like solids and whatever. Anyway, so I'm
not doing all הלכות בורר, hilchos borer, but I did want you
to be aware that this was a somewhat distinct category. So now
the גמרא Gemara goes back to the issue of אהל, ohel and
that's going to be for the rest of today. So let's take
a look. תני רמי
בר יחזקאל, Tani Rami bar Yechezkel, רמי בר יחזקאל Rami bar Yechezkel
taught: טלית כפולה לא יעשה. Tallis kfulah lo yeaseh. You should not
sort of make a
folded-over טלית. tallis. ואם עשה פטור אבל אסור, V'im asah patur aval
assur, but if you did you're exempt and you're not- but if
you did- so what's the case? So I'll tell you. But if
you did you're exempt, you're not חייב, but it's rabbinically forbidden. So
the case basically is that you have like four posts and you
spread a טלית tallis over to serve as a canopy. Okay, so
it's making a temporary canopy like an אהל עראי. ohel arai, כפול
Kful is bent? Yeah, so רש"י Rashi just says it means a
cloth doubled over. רש"י Rashi says that it means like it's not
only on top, but it falls over on the edges and becomes
a type of walls. Okay, so again, that's even worse than the
other cases because here it's really functioning as an אהל, ohel it's
just that it's temporary. Because it's temporary. What? כפוף Kafuf is bent,
right. כפול Kaful is like folded over, doubled, right. Okay, היה כרוך
עליה
חוט או משיכה, Hayah karuch aleha chut o meshichah, the bigger חידוש
chiddush here is what's מותר. mutar. Before we spoke about something that
was like on hinges and was made to, you know, would- was
made to unfold. Here he says similarly, if there is on it
some type of a string or like a or a strand, whatever,
another word for a string, מותר למותחו לכתחילה, mutar limotcho l'chat-chilah, you
can do it לכתחילה, l'chat-chilah, which basically means that, right, a drawstring
essentially. So it's basically already set up and you just have to
pull it open, so you're actually allowed to unfold it. And now
this is bigger because this isn't just like a hinge, but it's
a string, it's sort of now functioning even similar to a hinge.
Now תוספות Tosafos points out that there's an important other criteria here
because this isn't just something hinged. תוספות Tosafos says, look at תוספות
Tosafos כרוך עליה חוט או משיכה: Karuch Aleha Chut o Meshichah: כגון
ששיאר טפח בנין אחרי לא הוי ושרי. Kegon sheshiyer tefach binyan acharei
lo havei v'shari. Okay, and that actually is the הלכה halacha, that
if you have the little- כרך? kerach? תוספות? Tosafos? Just the first
few words. Okay, which basically is, the basic principle is, if you've
got something on hinges you can like open it up. If you've
got something rolled up and not on hinges, so you're doing something
more new by spreading it, right, and then you've got like a
string, then you can do it if you have the first טפח
tefach of the אהל ohel. already made. Because then you're just being
מוסיף mosif on an אהל ohel עראי, you're not making an אהל
עראי לכתחילה. ohel arai l'chat-chilah. Okay, so the requirement that the first
טפח tefach be there is by the case of the string, the
case of the hinges doesn't even really require it.
So ironically then you can make an actual אהל. ohel You know
these pop-up tents? Like you know you go to the beach, they
have these things? Yeah, they're like zip-up, they're like all you know
in plastic, you just throw it and then it- aren't
those-
but those are things you gotta do stuff, you gotta put it
into a hole or- no, nothing. Really, you just open it and
it- uh-huh. Could be, could be then if it really is all
just like opening up. You know what, so you know what is
an interesting issue here? The real interesting question is, although this is
more- this is less of an אהל ohel. and more of a
בונה boneh because of בונה boneh question or whatever, is those- when
I was had my infant- when my kids were infants, this was
a much bigger מלאכה. Now I think it's a lot easier. Is
those cribs. You know where you push down the center and or
whatever. Now I- I remember it would like take me like 20
minutes and whatever. Now they've got it so it's really simple, right?
Anyway, but that's- but that's- so- so it's interesting, at a certain
point if you're snapping things in place, that's a real בונה.
boneh. Right, but this is different, this is like you open up
a zipper and it just pops out.
Right, it's portable- yeah. Remember how hard those were?
Right.
Would that wouldn't be a problem, I mean that really is an
אהל? ohel.
Well, are you doing it? I mean, I guess the question is
דאורייתא though, right? Yeah. So these too, what do you think this
טלית tallis is? This טלית tallis is just to serve as an
אהל.
ohel Okay, but this is an actual אהל, ohel, you know what
I mean? It's called a pop-up tent.
Yeah.
Yeah, I understand. Okay, I'll have to get back to you on
that. But it could be if it ממש mamash also is all
hinged and does it by itself. All right, so now the גמרא
Gemara continues.
בעי מיניה רב כהנא מרב: Ba'ei minei Rav Kahana mi-Rav: כילה מהו?
Kilah mahu? What about a canopy on a bed? אמר ליה: Amar
lei, אף מיטה אסורה. Af mitah asurah. Why are you bothering asking
me about the canopy? Even to put up a bed is forbidden.
So he said- hold
on. מיטה? Mitah? What- well wait a minute, we're going to- it's
a little cute little exchange first and then we'll explain it. So
then he said, okay, מיטה מהו? mitah mahu? So really what's the
story with bed? אמר ליה: אף כילה מותרת. Af kilah muteres. Why
are you asking me about a bed? Even a canopy is permissible.
He was having a little fun with him. Okay, so he said,
כילה ומיטה מהו? Kilah u'mitah mahu? Okay, okay, so tell me about
both of them. אמר ליה, okay fine, כילה אסורה ומיטה מותרת. Kilah
asurah u'mitah muteres. The canopy you can't make- the canopy you can't
make, the bed is okay. So how do you explain all this?
It was like a little riddle. ולא קשיא. V'lo kashya. It's not
difficult. הא דקאמר אף מיטה אסורה. Ha d'ka'amar af mitah asurah. When
he said you can't even put up a bed, כדקרמנאי, k'de'karmonai, like
the Carmonians, which basically is some type of a bed which is
not just like a- you know like a- it wasn't just vertical
and you laid it down, you actually had to like snap the
legs into the- place and it could be a real concern
of even
בונה voneh not just because of אהל ohel but really like you're
building you're making the vessel or you might come to actually bang
it into place. הא דקאמר ליה אף כילה מותרת Ha d'ka'amar leh
af kila muteret when he said the canopy was permissible כרבי בר
יחזקאל k'Rabi bar Yechezkel like Rabi bar Yechezkel where you had a
string attached and it was just a draw string and as Tosafos
says maybe it was already had begun a טפח tefach so then
it's even you can even spread the canopy. Now the classic case
כילה אסורה ומיטה מותרת kila asura umita muteret like normal cases which
is to make the canopy from the outset is forbidden but to
put up a bed that was vertical and just to lie it
horizontal that would not be a problem. Okay.
What about מכה בפטיש makkeh b'patish in all these cases?
Well that's what Rashi seems to think the concern of כרמינאי karmina'ei
is is that if you start snapping the legs into place it
could be a מכה בפטיש makkeh b'patish or you might bang it
in and then be a מכה
בפטיש.
makkeh
b'patish.
But not on all the other ones?
Yeah the other cases is just you're just opening something. אמר רב
Amar Rav יוסף חזינא להו לכילתא דבי רב הונא Chazina lehu l'kilta
d'bei Rav Huna I saw the canopies of the house of Rav
Huna דמבאורתא נגידי d'me'orta negidi that they were spread in the evening
ומיצפרא חביטא רמיא umitzfra chavita ramya and in the morning they were
thrown down on the ground. So Rashi basically says that
basically makes that if they could undo them then you could also
do
them presumably still talking about a case where it had a drawstring
or something. Yeah חביטא רמיא chavita ramya is like thrown thrown and
banged down. No they both mean like thrown down. Okay.
אמר רב Amar Rav, משום רבי חייא mishum Rabi Chiya וילון vilon
now we've been talking about roofs how about walls? So if you
have a curtain מותר לנטותו mutar linto'oso you can actually hang a
curtain ומותר לפרקו umutar l'parko and you can remove it. Now this
is a whole question whether אהל ohel applies to walls as
well because the whole case about the פקק pkak and the חלון
chalon and the window Rashi says is a skylight but Tosafos speaks
about it even in window in a wall. So there are questions
about an issue about making walls if that's considered to be בונה
voneh or that's considered to be אהל. ohel. But certainly there's the
general assumption is that
if it's not being added to a permanent
structure like into a
house then making a wall
is an ארעי arai wall is not a problem. So basically you
can make what's called like a מחיצה של צניעותא. mechitzah shel tzniusa.
Actually the whole problem is making a מחיצה mechitzah if it's done
to serve a halachic function but that's another issue. So basically you
can spread a וילון vilon it's not talking about let's
say your shower curtain or if you've got the thing that separates
two rooms in your house and you've got some type of a
curtain you can hang your window curtains. Like attaching it to a
permanent structure is a different story but just hanging it just creating
a free-standing type of a curtain is a temporary curtain is not
a problem. That is not an אהל ohel. problem. ומותר לפרקו Umutar
l'parko and you can undo it. ואמר שמואל משום רבי חייא V'amar
Shmuel mishum Rabi Chiya Shmuel says in the name of Rabi
Chiya כילת חתנים kilas chasanim the canopy of
the wedding canopies. The wedding canopies were different than standard canopies and
then standard canopies what do they call like a four poster bed
were like literally like a roof. A wedding canopy was like a
teepee. Okay. So wedding canopies are better because it's defined as an
אהל ohel, you need there to be a טפח tefach width at
the top. So basically what we've seen here is that the walls
are okay temporary walls roofs are no good temporary roofs unless you
have something that makes it like either a drawstring or hinges or
something like that where you're not really making it new. But to
make a new temporary roof is a problem.
Is that to live in or just a חופה?
chuppah? No this was for I assume after they got married this
was in their honeymoon suite. Okay so but it was called the
כילת חתנים kilas chasanim and maybe it was only used the first
night of the wedding night but anyway but it was a type
of a this was a canopy under the bed.
It's okay because it doesn't have a טפח tefach roof?
Right it doesn't have a טפח tefach roof it goes to a
point so it's only considered a walls and walls are okay. It
was decorative? It was well I know also aesthetic and it was
for their wedding suite for their bedroom.
It was in itself a bedroom?
No on top of their bed they had inside a closed room
in their bedroom over their bed. Yeah right sure. Right. It was
a separate room? Exactly. Right okay yes. כילת חתנים מותר לנטותה Kilas
chasanim mutar linto'osah
so you can put it up on שבת ומותר לפרקה umutar l'parkah
and you can undo it and you can take it down because
it doesn't have a roof. אמר רב ששת בריה דרב אידי Amar
Rav Sheshes brei d'Rav Idi לא אמרן אלא שאין
בגגה טפח lo amran ela she'ein b'gagah tefach that's only if it
comes to a top at the point it's not a טפח tefach
wide. אבל יש בגגה טפח Aval yesh b'gagah tefach if at the
top of it where it comes the roof part of it where
the walls meet it has a טפח tefach wide אסורה asura that's
forbidden because then it's
an אהל. ohel, וכי אין בגגה טפח V'chi ein b'gagah tefach and
even when it doesn't come a
טפח tefach at the top נמי לא אמרן אלא שפחות משלושה סמוך
לגגה nami lo amran ela shepachus mishlosha samuch l'gagah that's only if
within three
טפחים tfachim it's not a טפח. tefach. Thanks. Okay.
Comes in like this. Now, but if within going three טפחים tefachim
down vertical or vertical from the point, it's a טפח tefach wide
here, you got a problem because all within three טפחים tefachim is
considered connected. So if within three טפחים tefachim down already the width
is three is one טפח tefach wide, then this one טפח tefach
width is considered the roof, it's like you flattened the top. Okay,
so it's not about that it doesn't come a point to the
top, but within three the top three טפחים tefachim of height to
not yet be a טפח tefach wide, because then you would imagine
it to be flattened. Okay. Now, then the next line here is
debated whether this is in the גמרא Gemara in the גמרא Gemara,
or not. ולא אמרן אלא שאין בשיפוע טפח. Velo amran ela she-ein
beshipua tefach. And we only say that that's also when there's not
in the angle טפח, tefach, in the in the in the incline.
אבל יש בשיפוע טפח, Aval yesh beshipua tefach, if there is in
the incline, שיפועי אהלים כאהלים דמי, shipuei ohalim ke-ohalim dami, then the
incline of tents is like tents. Now, what this means is is
that not only when you go a טפח tefach down can there
not be a טפח tefach wide here, but when you hit even
when you hit the bottom, right, and you look at just the
from the midpoint to the edge, it can't be a טפח tefach
wide, 'cause else you would look at the whole wall as if
it was a roof. Now of course if that's true, then at
the bottom it's only going to be...
give me a marker... anyway find another marker...
anyway fine, anyway you get the point, which is that if it
were if it were at the bottom, right, if it were here,
the point is is that if at the bottom from where it
ends from the midpoint to here's a טפח, tefach, then you look
at the entire wall here as if it is this wall separate
as if it's a roof. Now of course if that's true, רש"י
Rashi says, then how can you sit how can you use it?
The whole thing is two טפח tefach wide at the bottom, right?
Eight inches? What are you supposed to do? So רש"י Rashi says
oh okay this wasn't really used, this was just decorative that they
didn't even put over their bed, I don't even know where they
put it. תוספות Tosafot has an interesting suggestion, which is is that
it's sort of like it's it's not going straight down, it's like
going like like this, like so then you know so then and
and therefore each real point but anyway the easiest answer is that
this whole line doesn't belong here, 'cause it doesn't make sense to
think that just
you just have like one end and the other טפח. tefach.
Well if the if you have the bottom line, it can't be
from the two bottoms two טפח, tefach, it could be two טפח
tefach width. Anyway it's a very hard read in this גמרא, Gemara
so so תוספות Tosafot takes
it out.
ולא אמרן אלא דלא נחא מפורייא טפח. Velo amran ela delo necha
mipuraia tefach. And also it's only if it doesn't hang down from
the edge of the bed a טפח. tefach. אבל נחא מפורייא טפח
אסור. Aval necha mipuraia tefach asur. If you basically have, right, if
this cup here is the is the bed, right, if this cup
is the bed and this is your this thing going over. So
if it ended where the where like the mattress is, you're fine.
But if it kept kept on going down afterwards, then the part
that hang hung down below the edge of the mattress is considered
the wall and this whole thing is considered the roof. The reason
this works is because it's considered to be all wall and no
roof. But as soon as the edges hang down over the edges
of the bed, then those edges are the wall and the stuff
on top is a roof, so now you've got a problem. Okay,
the upshot of all of this being is that it's not a
problem if there's no roof, it's it's all considered if it's a
teepee and it's all walls, but under certain cases you have to
consider those walls of the teepee to be coming something like a
roof.
Now the גמרא Gemara goes on. ואמר רב ששת בריה דרב אידי
האי סיאנא שרי. Ve-amar Rav Sheshet brei de-Rav Idi hai siana shari.
This סיאנא siana is permissible. Now what is a סיאנא? siana? So
if you look רש"י Rashi writes כובא של לבד, kova shel levad,
it is a felt hat. There you go, Rivka. Don't worry, you
can wear your felt hat on שבת, it's not an אהל. ohel,
Now logically you would say because of like the reason of putting
up the bed, you know, the whole thing is already made, you're
just putting it on your head, you're not making something new, you're
not spreading it out, like the whole brim is already exists. So
the גמרא says one minute, ואיטמר סיאנא אסור, ve-itmar siana asur, but
don't we say that a סיאנא siana is forbidden? לא קשיא הא
דאיכא טפח הא דליכא טפח. Lo kashya ha de-ika tefach ha de-leika
tefach. It matters if there's a טפח tefach or not. Like we
said, it's only considered an אהל ohel. if it's got a טפח.
tefach. So now you have a brim that's bigger than a טפח,
tefach, which is four inches, some people do have very big brims.
Right, exactly. And now it's saying that you can't put it up,
so because you know again it's a little strange, right? How is
it different than all the other things that were already made that
you were able to do? Of course again here you could say
that here it's more functioning. as an אהל, ohel. right? Because your
hat, like the bed, the chair, the table, all those things are
not serving to protect the space underneath. The point of the hat
is to give shade to underneath, which is exactly what an אהל
ohel. is supposed to be. Of course, again, it's funny because it's
something you all walk around with. An אהל ohel, also has the
sense of like a structure that's independent of you, not something that's
like constantly moving with you.
But anyways, right, you know, it moves.
So let's see what the גמרא says, we're not done. So the
גמרא says, אלא מעתה says the גמרא, שרטיה דגלימא טפח הכא נמי
דמיחייב shartaya deglima tefach hacha nami demichayev or דאסור, de'assur, different גרסא.
girsa. If you took your cloak and you put it over your
head, let's say it was raining, right, or something like that, and
you did like this with your cloak. It's אסור assur because you're
doing it now to protect yourself, right? It's a טפח tefach and
so on. So come on, this whole thing, clothing should be different,
or this degree of, you know, portability should make it different and
so on. So the גמרא says, אלא you're right, לא קשיא. lo
kashya. It's not difficult. הא דמהדק הא דלא מהדק. ha de'mahedik ha
de'lo mahedik. The difference is whether it's on tightly or not tightly.
Now what difference does that make? So רש"י Rashi says that it
has nothing to do with an אהל. ohel, He says the problem
is if it's not tight, you're afraid the wind will pick it
off and you'll come racing after it and carry it and the
whole concern about carrying it in a רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim. And
now the issue of hat is completely not related to אהל. תוספות
Tosafot says however, if you look at תוספות Tosafot הא דמהדק ha
de'mahedik tight, פירש ר"ח שאינו נכפף דאז נראה כעין אהל. peirush Rach
she'eino nichpaf de'az nireh ke'ein ohel. It's not, it doesn't like mean
the brim is stiff, it doesn't, it's not doesn't easily like bend.
Then it's an אהל, then it looks like an אהל, it's not
really an אהל, but looks like an אהל. ולא מהדק, ve'lo mahedik,
שהוא נכפף, she'hu nichpaf, if it's more flexible, אז לא נראה כעין
אהל. az lo nireh ke'ein ohel. So according to this, if you
have a stiff brim of a hat you would not be able,
you'd not be able, and this is brought down in שולחן ערוך
Shulchan Aruch and but I see if I remember correctly I didn't
double check both positions, I mean obviously in practice we do not
say that hats are a problem, which really follows רש"י, Rashi, but
there is some discussion around it, around you know if you read
it like רבנו חננאל, Rabbeinu Chananel, you can't wear hats that have
stiff brims. Okay, now the גמרא says, שלח ליה רמי בר יחזקאל,
shlach lei Rami bar Yechezkel, so we quoted רמי בר יחזקאל Rami
bar Yechezkel a little while ago with the, with the drawstring. So
he sent to רב הונא, Rav Huna, אימא לן איזי הני מילי
מעלייתא דאמרת לן משמיה דרב. eima lan eezy hanei meilei ma'alyata de'amart
lan mishmeih de'Rav. Tell us, easy, which could just mean word like
in truth and faith, you know some of those good teachings that
you used to say in the name of רב. Rav חד בשבת
וחד בתורה. chad beShabbat vechad beTorah. One relating to הלכות שבת hilchos
Shabbat and one relating to Torah. Well he, I think he knew
what the teachings were, he wasn't fishing, but you know he wanted
to hear him repeat it. So and he wanted maybe to have
him write it down because he sent him a letter, so he
wanted you know, so he was a little leading the witness, but
he wanted this to be recorded as an official teaching. So שלח
ליה, shlach lei, he sent back to him, הא דתניא, ha detanya,
so
here's teaching number one about שבת. גוד, gud, remember this piece of
the גוד, gud, like the flask, the, you know, the leather flask
that you would support up in the wind and that would be
a type of a דרבנן problem of אהל. So גוד בכיסנא מותר
לנטותו בשבת. gud bekisna mutar lintoto beShabbat. So רש"י Rashi says,
גוד בכיסנא, gud bekisno, רש"י Rashi says right,
with, if you put, רש"י Rashi says גוד בכיסנא gud bekisno means
by its two, what, straps? If you use the
straps ומותר לנטותו u'mutar lintoto on שבת. So אמר רב, and רב
says, לא שנו אלא בבי תרי בני אדם, lo shanu ela be'bei
terei bnei adam, that's only if two people are putting it up.
אבל באדם אחד, aval be'adam echad, if one person, אסור, assur, forbidden.
רש"י Rashi says he doesn't even really understand the difference, he quotes
גאונים, Geonim, apparently if it's one person what you would have to
do is, you know, you have to tie it on one end
and like really stretch it to tie it to the other post
so that it would be suspended for it, and it would look
more like an אהל. If it's two people, you know, if you
have people at each end, you can do it more loosely apparently.
I mean you sort of understand the mechanic, like if you have
to, you know, if I've got to set a tablecloth by myself,
right, I put one end down, I would have to like I
don't know put books on to keep it solid and then I'd
stretch it to the other end. Somehow because you have to do
it yourself you got to make it tighter at the ends whereas
if you do two people it can be looser. Something along those
lines. But if it's one person then it's very tight, it's more
like an אהל, it's a problem. אמר אביי, ובכילה, u'bekila, אפילו בי
עשרה בני אדם אסור. afilu bei assara bnei adam assur. And the
כילה, kila, which is what we talked about, the thing that really
is made for an אהל, like a type of a roof, okay,
that even if you have ten people doing it it's forbidden, because
why, אי אפשר דלא מימתחה פורתא. ee efshar delo mimtacha purta. It's
impossible that it would not be stretched a little bit. Now this
whole idea of stretching is not clear what the concern around stretching
is, but it seems that somehow by stretching it if it's loose
then it's just like you put something on. If it's stretched it's
more like a, you know, it's more tight, it's more like a
roof. Okay. אידך
מאי היא, idach mai hee, what's the other
teaching? דתניא, detanya, כירה שנשמטה אחת מירכותיה. kira shenishmeta achat miyarkoteiha. If
you have an oven that one of its legs has, it's like
it was on a tripod, three legs, and one of its legs
has slipped off. מותר לטלטלה, mutar letaltela, you can still move it
around because it can still, it's still not מוקצה, muktzeh, it can
still be
used. שתים אסור. shtayim assur. two legs are broken, then presumably maybe
it's a מוקצה *muktzah* problem or maybe we're concerned you'll come to
fix it. רבא אמר אפילו חד נמי אסור *Rava amar afilu chad
nami assur*, even if only one leg has slipped off, you can't
move it on שבת *Shabbos*. גזירה שמא יגסוף *Gezeira shema yigsof*, forget
מוקצה *muktzah*, it's a concern that if one leg is off, you'll
come to stick in the other leg and fix it. And that
could be like a בונה *boneh* or מכה בפטיש *makeh b'patish* problem.
Okay, so those are the two teachings of שבת *Shabbos* and obviously
the connection was רמי בר יחזקאל *Rami bar Yechezkel* and the idea
of אהל *ohel*. And now we're going to take a nice little
digression into areas of אגדתא *agadata*. Okay, תורה *Torah*. Now what's the
issue relating to תורה *Torah*? That's pretty generic, but obviously he had
something in mind. דאמר רב *De'amar Rav* because רב *Rav* says עתידה
תורה שתשתכח מישראל *atidah torah shetishtakach miyisroel*, there'll be a time when
תורה *Torah* will be forgotten from the Jewish people.
וכי לא תשתכח מפי זרעו
*V'chi lo tishtakach mipi zaro*, okay, שנאמר *shene'emar* as the פסוק *pasuk*
says. I mean that was the time when they found the ספר
sefer תורה *Sefer Torah* in the time of what's his name, right?
יאשיהו המלך *Yoshiyahu Hamelech*. It sounded like they had forgotten the תורה
*Torah*, right? So anyway, there'll be a time when תורה *Torah* will
be forgotten in Israel. שנאמר והפלא ה' את מכותך *Shene'emar v'hifla Hashem
et makotecha*, God will increase your smitings. הפלאה זו *Hafla'ah zo* איני
יודע
מה היא *eini yodeia mah hi*. This idea of הפלאה *hafla'ah*, wonder
or increase, I don't know what it's referring to. כשהוא אומר לכן
הנני יוסיף להפליא את העם הזה הפלא ופלא *Kshehu omer lachen hineni
yosif l'hafli et ha'am hazeh haflei vafela*, I will continue to do
wonders or whatever against this people, wonders and wonders upon wonders. והרי
הוא אומר הפלאה זו תורה *V'harei hu omer hafla'ah zo Torah*, this
is תורה *Torah*. Now how do you know? Because the end of
the פסוק *pasuk* as רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, says ואבדה חכמת חכמיו
*v'avdah chochmat chachamav*. The wisdom of its sages will be lost. Okay,
so since it says הפלא ופלא *haflei vafela* by losing the wisdom,
somehow this means תורה *Torah*, that the sort of like a wondrous
smiting, not in the good sense of wondrous,
of a punishment is the loss of תורה *Torah*. תנו רבנן *Tanu
rabanan*, כשנכנסו רבותינו לכרם ביבנה *kshenichnasu raboteinu l'kerem b'Yavne*. Now we're going
to see the significance of this statement. When our rabbis entered into
the כרם ביבנה Kerem B'Yavneh *Kerem b'Yavne*, meaning after the חורבן הבית
*Churban HaBayit* and they set up the ישיבה *yeshiva* in יבנה *Yavne*.
It was called a vineyard because they were sort of like arranged
with rows like a vineyard. אמרו
*Amru* they said עתידה תורה שתשתכח מישראל *atidah Torah shetishtakach miyisroel*. This
is in a תוספתא דעדיות *Tosefta d'Eduyot*. This is explaining why they
did the process of getting testimony, people to come and testify all
the things that they had heard about תורה שבעל פה *Torah sheba'al
peh* because they were afraid. They felt like we have to consolidate
all the information, we have to organize it because we're afraid it'll
all be lost. I mean ultimately it led to the writing of
the משנה *Mishnah*. Even though it was תורה שבעל פה *Torah sheba'al
peh* and you weren't supposed to write it down and so on,
the משנה *Mishnah* wasn't actually literally written, but nevertheless the creation of
sort of like concretizing it was a concern that the information was
being lost and that concern was particularly heightened post-חורבן *Churban*. So they
said עתידה תורה שתשתכח מישראל *atidah Torah shetishtakach miyisroel*. There'll be a
time God forbid the תורה *Torah* will be forgotten in Israel. שנאמר
הנה ימים באים נאם ה' אלוהים והשלחתי רעב בארץ *Shene'emar hinei yamim
ba'im neum Hashem Elokim v'hishlachti ra'av ba'aretz*, I'll send a hunger in
the land. לא רעב ללחם ולא צמא למים *Lo ra'av lalechem v'lo
tzama lamayim*, not hunger for bread or thirst for water. כי אם
לשמוע דברי ה' *Ki im lishmoa divrei Hashem*, but to hear the
word of God. So of course this is what we see now
at שלוש סעודות *shalosh seudos* like it's a positive thing, like this
thirsty here for God, but what it's sort of speaking about is
the fact
that there'll be the famine, that nobody will have knowledge of God.
וכתיב *Uchitiv* and the verse says ונעו מים עד ים *V'na'u miyam
ad yam*. And the waters will move to the ocean. ומצפון ועד
מזרח ישוטטו *Umitzafon v'ad mizrach yishotetu* and from north to east they
will spread out לבקש את דבר ה' *levakesh et devar Hashem* to
find, to seek out the word of God. ולא ימצאו *V'lo yimtza'u*
and they won't find it. So there'll be a time when people
won't be able to be hungry for תורה *Torah* but they won't,
nobody will know it. דבר ה' *Devar Hashem*. Now what's דבר ה'
*devar Hashem*? זו הלכה *Zu halacha*. That's הלכה *halacha*. People, those four
words is very common, is a commonly repeated phrase. דבר ה' זו
הלכה *Devar Hashem zu halacha*. So anyway one understanding of דבר ה'
*devar Hashem* is הלכה *halacha*. או דבר ה' זה הקץ *O devar
Hashem zeh haketz*, or it means knowledge of the messianic times. או
דבר ה' זו נבואה *O devar Hashem zu nevuah*, it's prophecy. So
people will be seeking either to know the end of times or
prophecy. Those two at least make sense that sense of, but the
first interpretation is that they won't even know הלכה *halacha* and that
there'll be a hunger for that and there'll be an absence of
that and they won't be able to find it. ומהו ישוטטו לבקש
את דבר ה' *U'mahu yishotetu levakesh et devar Hashem*? What it means
that they'll spread out to find it? So אמרו *Amru* עתידה אשה
שתיטול כיכר של תרומה *atidah ishah shetitol kikar shel terumah*. So here's
the example of like spreading out. A woman will take a loaf
of תרומה *terumah* ותחזור בבתי כנסיות ובבתי מדרשות *v'tachzor b'vatei knesiyot u'vatei
midrashot* and she'll go to synagogues and to study halls. לידע אם
טמא היא ואם טהור היא *Leda im tamei hi v'im tahor hi*.
She'll be spreading as it were she's the one spreading out to
find דבר ה' *devar Hashem*. She's trying to find out is this
pure, impure. ואין מבין אם טהור היא ואם טמא היא *V'ein mevin
im tahor hi v'im tamei hi*. Nobody will be able to know.
So there'll be just
like total ignorance. בהדיא כתיב ביה *Behedya ketiv bei*, what do you
mean?
It says explicitly מכל האוכל אשר יאכל *mikol ha'ochel asher ye'achel*. So
you know it's a פסוק *pasuk*. Presumably they're not going to forget
פסוקים *psukim* in the תורה *Torah*. And the פסוק *pasuk* says that
if something טמא *tamei* touches something טהור *tahor* it becomes טמא *tamei*.
So how could they totally be ignorant? אלא *Ela*, okay here's what
she won't know. לדעת אם ראשונה היא ואם שנייה היא *leda'at im
rishona hi ve'im shniya hi*. So he wants to know ואין מבין
*ve'ein meivin*. So somebody, I'm sorry, I think I put the comma
in the wrong place before. First it said לדעת אם טהורה היא
ואם טמאה היא, אם טמאה היא ואם טהורה היא ואין מבין *leda'at
im tahora hi ve'im tmeia hi, im tmeia hi ve'im tahora hi
ve'ein meivin*, nobody will know. And then the גמרא *Gemara* challenges it:
אם טהורה היא ואם טמאה היא, בהדיא כתיבי בה *im tahora hi
ve'im tmeia hi, behedya ketivei bah*. Just simple תורה *Torah* טמא *tamei*
טהור *tahor* it says explicitly מכל האוכל אשר יאכל *mikol ha'ochel asher
ye'achel*. אלא לדעת *ela leda'at* he wants to know אם ראשונה היא
ואם שנייה היא *im rishona hi ve'im shniya hi*. Yes, she knows
it's טמא *tamei* or they know it's טמא *tamei*, but the question
is is it an אב לטומאה *av letuma* or ראשון לטומאה *rishon
letuma* or שני לטומאה *sheni letuma*? ואין מבין *ve'ein meivin* and nobody
will know. So the גמרא *Gemara* says: הא נמי מתניתין היא *ha
nami matnitin hi*. What do you mean? What, they'll forget a משנה
*Mishna* to know? What, they'll forget a משנה *Mishna* because of a
רבא *Rava*? I know, exactly. It's a משנה *Mishna*: השרץ שנמצא בתנור
*hasheretz shenimtza batanur*, if you have a dead rodent in an oven,
a pottery oven, הפת שבתוכו שנייה *hapat shebetocho shniya*, the bread inside
is a שני *sheni* because the rodent is an אב *av*, it
makes the oven a ראשון *rishon*, the ראשון *rishon* makes the bread
a שני *sheni*. שהתנור תחילה *shehatanur techila* because the oven itself is
a ראשון *rishon*. So anyway, how could they, you know, it's pretty
straightforward, how could they this much they won't know? Really that degree
of ignorance? So גמרא *Gemara* says no: מיסתפקא להו *mistapkalu hu* here's
the doubt they'll have. הא דאמר ליה רב אדא בר אהבה לרבא
*hada amlei Rav Adda bar Ahava leRava*, so רב אדא בר אהבה
*Rav Adda bar Ahava* said to רבא *Rava*, I don't get why
the bread is a שני *sheni* and not a ראשון *rishon*. Why?
לחזי האי תנורא כמאן דמלי טומאה דמי *lechazei hai tanura keman demale
tuma dami*, why not see that if the rodent is in the
תנור *tanur*, it's like the תנור *tanur* is filled with טומאה *tuma*,
ותהוי פת ראשונה *vetehavi פת rishona*, and it's like the rodent directly
is מטמא *metamei* the פת *pat*. Why does it only מטמא *metamei*
the oven and the oven מטמא *metamei* the פת *pat*? So therefore,
yes, they'll know the laws that things are טמא *tamei* and טהור
*tahor*, but they'll forget basic factors, they'll forget the idea, they'll have
an argument to say it's a reasonable argument: if there's a rodent
in the oven and a bread in the oven, it should make
the oven a ראשון *rishon* maybe, maybe the rodent should directly be
מטמא *metamei* the ראשון *rishon* and they'll forget the idea that that's
not how the טומאה *tuma* works. The טומאה *tuma* works by saying
that the rodent makes the oven טמא *tamei* and the oven makes
the bread טמא *tamei*. So that's what they'll forget. אמר ליה *amlei*,
לא אמרינן לחזי האי תנורא כמאן דמלי טומאה דמי *lo amrinan lechazei
hai tanura keman demale tuma dami*, so anyway to end this he
said: no, we don't look at it like it's filled with טומאה
*tuma*. דתניא *detanya*, יכול יהיו כל הכלים מיטמאין באוויר כלי חרס *yacholu
kol hakelim mitamin be'avir kli cheres*, maybe we should say this: that
if you have anything in the airspace of a vessel with a
dead rodent, maybe they will directly get the טומאה *tuma* from the
טמא *tamei* thing, okay, not that the טמא *tamei* thing will make
the oven טמא *tamei* and the oven make the things in it
טמא *tamei*, but maybe the dead טמא *tamei* thing will directly make
the things in the oven טמא *tamei*. תלמוד לומר *talmud lomar*, so
the verse says: כל אשר בתוכו יטמא מכל האוכל אשר יאכל *kol
asher betocho yitma mikol ha'ochel asher ye'achel*, anything in the oven together
with this rodent will be טמא *tamei* if it's food. אוכלין מיטמאין
באוויר כלי חרס ואין כלים מיטמאין באוויר כלי חרס *ochlin mitamin be'avir
kli cheres ve'ein kelim mitamin be'avir kli cheres*, only food and not
vessels. Why is this? Because if you remember, I mentioned this a
couple times,
vessels and people can become a ראשון *rishon*, but only food can
become a שני *sheni*. So the תורה *Torah* basically says if you
have a dead rodent in an oven and you have food, the
food will become טמא *tamei*. And חז"ל *Chazal* understand what that means
is only food, if you had a vessel not. Now, the only
reason to say that food could become טמא *tamei* and not a
vessel is to say that it's becoming a שני *sheni*. Okay, because
when we know that food can be a שני *sheni* and vessels
cannot be a שני *sheni*. So how is it that the food
becomes a שני *sheni*? The rodent is an אב *av*. So it
must be the rodent doesn't make the food directly טמא *tamei*, then
it would be a ראשון *rishon*. It must be the rodent makes
the oven טמא *tamei* and then things that are in the oven
become טמא *tamei* through the oven, and therefore they become a שני
*sheni*. So that because the mechanics works that way, the rodent to
the oven, the oven to the stuff inside of it is only
by food which can be a שני *sheni*, not by vessels. So
anyway, but there would be a logical argument to have thought everything,
the rodent and the food are in the oven at the same
time, it's like they become טמא *tamei*, you know, it's like they
directly become טמא *tamei*. So you could have thought, so that type
of an ignorance, that's what the woman is running around
trying to get an answer, is
it a ראשון *rishon* or a שני *sheni*? And nobody knows.
So it doesn't really mean the תורה *Torah* is forgotten, this is
such a minor, a trivia.
Right,
I mean it's not the most obscure type of detail. Like if
you've learned טומאה וטהרה *Tuma ve'Tahara*, it's pretty much there. But it's
right, but it's not like, right, it's like the obvious stuff isn't
forgotten, exactly, exactly. That's the גמרא *Gemara*'s pushback. The גמרא *Gemara* doesn't
want to believe that basic stuff will be forgotten.
Well, it, I would say today that women do run around to
רבנים *Rabbis* for one to the other for help and there is
no help.
Right,
right, that's a different issue than the תורה *Torah* is forgotten. Okay,
good point, good point. Exactly. Right, I get it. Exactly. Okay, so
anyway so here the גמרא *Gemara* has pushed back and said that,
you know, fine, basic הלכות *halachos* of טומאה *tuma* that there is
טומאה *tuma*, yes. But when you get to even like one level
beyond that, you know, how does the טומאה *tuma* work in an
oven, in a כלי חרס *kli cheres*, that already that level of
clarity will be forgotten. תניא *Tanya*, we learned in the ברייתא *baraita*,
רבי שמעון בן יוחאי אומר *Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai omer*: חס ושלום
*chas veshalom* שתשתכח תורה מישראל *shetishtakach Torah miYisrael*. God forbid there will
ever be a time that תורה *Torah* will be forgotten from ישראל
*Yisrael*, שנאמר *shene'emar* as the
verse says: כי לא תשכח *ki lo tishach*... Check it out, Michael.
אלא מה אני מקיים ישוטטו לבקש את דבר ה' ולא ימצאו? ishoshutu
l'vakesh et devar Hashem v'lo yimtza'u? They'll look to find and they
won't find. שלא ימצאו, Shelo yimtza'u, here's what they won't find: הלכה
ברורה ומשנה ברורה במקום אחד. halacha berurah u'mishnah berurah b'makom echad. Clear
הלכה, clear teaching in one place. So as רש''י says what it
means is, first of all, that's where the משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah
gets its phrase משנה ברורה. Mishnah Berurah. So,
but הלכה ברורה halacha berurah and משנה ברורה, mishnah berurah, there's also
a ספר called הלכה ברורה halacha berurah as well. Anyway, it would
mean that, yes, nobody's gonna forget it, but everything will be debated.
There'll be a lot, nothing will be clear, so which also can
explain why you needed the whole כרם ביבנה and you needed the
עדויות Eduyos and you needed to record the teachings and you needed
to pull it together, because we're not saying that they'll forget it,
but they'll just always be debating every little detail. So nothing will
be black and white. Okay,
so we will see more about all of this tomorrow.